Register of the Geoffrey White Papers, 1939-1965
Hoover Institution Archives
Geoffrey White Papers,
1939-1965
78106
White, Geoffrey
16 manuscript boxes, 1 box of slides 6.9 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Correspondence, writings, reports, resolutions, minutes, discussion bulletins, and printed matter, relating to American Trotskyist politics, the Socialist Workers Party, and the formation of the Spartacist League. Includes a few items relating to the Communist Party of the United States and the Independent Socialist League.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1978.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
1939 Joined the Communist Party of the United States
1957 Resigned from the Communist Party and subsequently joined the Socialist Workers' Party
1963 Supported James Robertson who split the Socialist Workers' Party and established a new Marxist group, Spartacist
Access Points
Communist Party of the United States of America.; Fourth International.; Independent Socialist League.; Socialist Workers Party.; Spartacist League of the U.S.; Communism.; Communism--United States.; Socialism--United States.; United States--Politics and government.
Series Description
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1961-1963. (Box Box 1.)
  Arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent.
- SUBJECT FILE, 1940-1965. (Box Boxes 1-4)
  Analysis, announcements, bibliography, bulletins, chronology, clippings, declarations, drafts of resolutions, leaflets, letters, maps, memoranda, minutes, notes, ordinances, outline of a speech, petitions, proposed agenda of a meeting, reports, resolutions, statements, statistics, statutes, summary of a discussion, theses, typed copies of magazine articles. Arranged alphabetically by subject.
- ISSUANCES BY LEFT WING ORGANIZATIONS, 1939-1965. (Box Boxes 4-10)
  Mimeographed discussion and internal bulletins, printed matter. Arranged alphabetically by issuing agency.
- AUDIO-VISUAL. (Cassette Cassette drawer)
  Slides, Arranged by subject.
Container List
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1961-1963
  - Unidentified, 1961-1963 (9) (Box 1., Folder 1)
  - Coover, Oscar, 1961-1963 (7) (Folder 2)
  - Curtis, Carol, 1962-1963 (8) (Folder 3)
  - Dobbs, Farrel, 1962-1963 (3) (Folder 4)
  - Fox, Art, 1962 (2) (Folder 5)
  - Freeman, Danny, 1962 (1) (Folder 6)
  - Harper, Lynne, 1962-1963 (8) (Folder 7)
  - Healy, Gerry, 1961-1963 (12) (Folder 8)
  - Hoskins, Wally, 1963 (2) (Folder 9)
  - Ireland, Larry, 1962 (5) (Folder 10)
  - Kerry, Tom, 1963 (2) (Folder 11)
  - Mage, Shane, 1963 (1) (Folder 12)
  - Michaels, Sharlotte, 1962 (2) (Folder 13)
  - Newsletter, 1961 (1) (Folder 14)
  - Phillips, Wendell, 1962 (4) (Folder 15)
  - Robertson, James, 1961-1963 (62) (Folder 16)
  - Socialist Workers' Party. Political Committee, 1963 (1) (Folder 17)
  - Wohlforth, Tim, 1961-1963 (65) (Folder 18)
- SUBJECT FILE, 1940-1965
  - Berkeley, California -- Election, 1959. Arranged by Geoffrey White. Announcements, bulletins, chronology, clippings, instructions, leaflets, maps, notes, ordinances, petitions, photographs, printed matter, program, statements, summary of a speech, 1958-1959 (Box 1., Folder 19-20)
  - California -- Gubernatorial Election, 1962. Letter, proposal, 1962 (Folder 21)
  - Christian Anti-Communist Crusade. Statement, 1962 (Box 2., Folder 1)
  - Colonial Problem, Analysis, statement, typed copies of magazine articles, 1961 (Folder 2)
  - Communist Party of the United States. Draft of a program, comments, letters, notes, statements, statistics, 1956-1957 (Folder 3)
  - Cuba. Clippings, draft of a resolution, outline of a speech, reports, statements, 1961-1963 (Folder 4)
  - Cuban Missile Crisis. Declaration, letter, minutes, statement 1962 (Folder 5)
  - Militant Labor Civil Rights Committee. Local 1199-65 Caucus. Minutes, 1967-1968 (Folder 6)
  - Nuclear Weapon. Letter, 1962 (Folder 7)
  - Peace Movement. Clippings, reports, 1962 (Folder 8)
  - Progressive Labor Group. Letter, memorandum, 1963 (Folder 9)
  - Sino-Soviet Conflict. Letter, statements, 1963 (Folder 10)
  - Socialist Workers' Party. East Bay Branch -- Propaganda Work. Letter, statements, 1961-1962 (Folder 11)
  - Socialist Workers' Party. East Bay Branch -- Structure and Composition. Notes, reports, statement, statistics, 1960-1961 (Folder 12)
  - Socialist Workers' Party -- Political and Tactical Issues. Draft of a resolution, proposals, reports, resolution, 1940-1943 (?) (Folder 13)
  - Socialist Workers' Party -- Structure and Composition. Letters, minutes, notes, statutes, 1954-1962 (Folder 14)
  - Trotskyist Movement -- Inner Struggle
    - Chile. Letters, 1961-1962 (Folder 15)
    - International Level
      - General. Bibliography, draft of a resolution, letters, reports, statements, 1961-1963 (Folder 16)
      - Dobbs, Farrel; Healy, Gerry; Preston, G. Letters, 1962-1963 (Folder 17)
      - Fourth International. Extraordinary Conference, April 1962. Statement, 1962 (Folder 18)
      - Fourth International. Secretariat. Letter, 1961 (Folder 19)
      - Mage, Shane. Theses, 1962 (Folder 20)
      - Robertson, James. Letters, summary of a discussion,, 1962-1963 (Folder 21)
      - Socialist Labor League. National Committee. Letter, statement, 1962 (Folder 22)
      - Socialist Workers' Party. Political Committee. Statement, 1962 (Folder 23)
      - Socialist Workers' Party. Reorganized Minority Tendency. Statement, letter, 1963 (Folder 24)
      - White, Geoffrey. Statement, 1962 (Folder 25)
    - United States
      - General. Announcement, letters (including those of Steve Fox, James Robertson, and Tim Wohlforth), reports, resolutions, statements, theses, 1961-1965 (Folder 26)
      - Selected Documents. Arranged by Geoffrey White. Letters, minutes, notes, proposal, receipt, reports, statements, summary of a discussion, 1962-1964 (Box 3., Folder 1-3)
      - Dobbs, Farrel. Letter, 1963 (Folder 4)
      - Fox, Steve. Letters, 1963 (Folder 5)
      - Harper, Lynne. Letters, 1962-1963 (Folder 6)
      - Healy, Gerry. Letter, 1962 (Folder 7)
      - Ireland, Larry. Statements, 1962 (Folder 8)
      - Mage, Shane. Letter, theses, 1962 (Folder 9)
      - Robertson, James. Letters, 1961-1963 (Folder 10)
      - Socialist Workers' Party. Control Commission. Report, 1963 (Folder 11)
      - Socialist Workers' Party. East Bay Branch. Minutes, 1960-1963 (Folder 12)
      - Socialist Workers' Party. Political Committee. Resolution, 1963 (Folder 13)
      - Socialist Workers' Party. Revolutionary Tendency. Bay Area Group. Minutes, 1962-1963 (Folder 14)
      - Socialist Workers' Party. Revolutionary Tendency. East Bay Group. Minutes, 1962-1963 (Folder 15)
      - Socialist Workers' Party. Revolutionary Tendency. National Caucus. Minutes, 1963 (Folder 16)
      - Socialist Workers' Party. Revolutionary Tendency. New York Group. Minutes, 1962-1963 (Folder 17)
      - White Geoffrey. Statement, summary of James Robertson's position, 1962 (Folder 18)
      - Wohlforth, Tim. Letters, report, statements, 1961-1963 (Folder 19)
  - United Socialist Action. Bay Area, California. Letters, minutes, proposed agenda of a meeting, statement of principles, 1958-1959 (Folder 20)
  - United States -- Black People Problem. Leaflet, letters, reports, 1953-1963 (Folder 21)
  - United States -- Civil Rights. Analysis of the Francis Amendment, statement, 1962-1963 (Folder 22)
  - United States -- Labor Movement. History of the labor movement, letters, proposal, 1962 (Box 4., Folder 1)
  - United States--- Presidential Election, 1960. Letter, 1960 (Folder 2)
  - United States -- Socialist Movement
    - National Conference, 28-30 November 1958. Letter, minutes, 1958-1959 (Folder 3)
    - Youth Organizations. Letters, notes, reports, statements, theses, 1957-1962 (Folder 4)
- ISSUANCES BY LEFT WING ORGANIZATIONS, 1939-1965
  - Miscellany. Printed matter, 1947-1965 (Box 4., Folder 5)
  - Communist Party of Eastern Pennsylvania -- Discussion Bulletin, 1956 (vol. 1, no. 2) (Folder 6)
  - Communist Party of the United States -- Discussion Bulletin, n.d. (Folder 7)
  - Fourth International. International Committee -- International Bulletin, 1961-1963 (?) (nos. 6, 7, 9, 10, 14, 16) (Folder 8)
  - Socialist Workers' Party
    - Bulletin of Marxist Studies
      - 1957 (no. 1) (Folder 9)
      - 1958 (no. 2) (Folder 10)
    - Discussion Bulletin
      - 1940 (vol. 3, no. 1) (Folder 11)
      - 1944 (April) (Folder 12)
      - 1950 (no. 4) (Folder 13)
      - 1951 (no. 7) (Folder 14)
      - 1953 (no. A-12) (Folder 15)
      - 1954
        - Nos. A-14, A-15, A-19, A-20, A-22 (Folder 16)
        - Nos. A-23, A-25, A-26 (Box 5., Folder 1)
      - 1955, (nos. A-27 -- A-33) (Folder 2)
      - 1956, (vol 17, nos. 1, 2) (Folder 3)
      - 1957
        - Vol. 18, nos. 1-3, 8 (Folder 4)
        - Vol. 18, nos. 10, 12, 13 (Folder 5)
      - 1958 (vol. 19, no. 3) (Folder 6)
      - 1959
        - Vol. 20, nos. 1-5 (Folder 7)
        - Vol. 20, nos. 6-10 (Folder 8)
        - Vol. 20, nos. 11-14, 16 (Folder 9)
      - 1960 (vol. 21, nos. 1, 2, 4) (Box 6., Folder 1)
      - 1961
        - Vol. 22, nos. 1-4 (Folder 2)
        - Vol. 22, nos. 5-7, 9, 10, 13 (Folder 3)
        - Vol. 22, nos. 14-19 (Folder 4)
      - 1962
        - Vol. 23, nos. 2-5 (Folder 5)
        - Vol. 23, nos. 6, 8-10 (Folder 6)
      - 1963
        - Vol. 24, nos. 1-6 (Folder 7)
        - Vol. 24, nos. 7-10 (Box 7., Folder 1)
        - Vol, 24, nos. 13-19 (Folder 2)
        - Vol. 24, nos. 20-25 (Folder 3)
        - Vol. 24, nos. 26-29 (Folder 4)
        - Vol. 24, nos. 31, 32, 34 (Folder 5)
      - 1965 (?) (vol. 25, nos. 2, 6, 8, 12, 14) (Folder 6)
    - Internal Bulletin
      - 1939 (May, no. 8; vol. 2, nos. 1-5) (Folder 7)
      - 1940 (vol. 2, nos. 6, 7, 11-13) (Folder 8)
      - 1943 (vol. 5, no. 5) (Box 8., Folder 1)
      - 1944 (vol. 6, no. 6) (Folder 2)
      - 1945 (vol. 7, nos. 5, 11, 13) (Folder 3)
      - 1946 (vol. 8, nos. 3, 7, 10, 12, 14) (Folder 4)
      - 1947 (vol. 9, nos. 5, 7) (Folder 5)
      - 1948 (vol. 10, nos. 2, 4) (Folder 6)
      - 1949 (vol. 11, nos. 1, 5) (Folder 7)
      - 1951 (vol. 13, no. 1) (Folder 8)
      - 1952 (vol. 14, no. 2) (Folder 9)
      - 1953
        - Vol. 15, nos. 1-10 (Folder 10)
        - Vol. 15, nos. 12, 14, 15 (Folder 11)
        - Vol. 15, nos. 16, 17, 19 (Folder 12)
      - 1954 (vol. 16, nos. 1, 2) (Box 9., Folder 1)
      - 1939-1959 -- Bulletin List (Folder 2)
    - International Information Bulletin (Folder 3)
      - 1953 (September) (Folder 3)
      - 1954 (January) (Folder 4)
      - 1961 (March, April) (Folder 5)
      - 1962 (March) (Folder 6)
      - 1963 (May, July) (Folder 7)
      - 1964 (January, May) (Folder 8)
    - Party Campaigner, 1960 (vol. 1, no. 1) (Folder 9)
  - Socialist Workers' Party. Bay Area Branch -- Discussion Bulletin
    - 1950 (vol. 3, no. 2) (Folder 10)
    - 1954 (?) (Folder 11)
  - Spartacist
    - Marxist Bulletin, n.d. (no. 2) (Folder 12)
    - Spartacist
      - 1964 (November) (Folder 13)
      - 1965 (June) (Folder 14)
      - 1966 (July, August, September) (Folder 15)
  - Young Socialist Alliance -- Discussion Bulletin, 1963 (vol. 7, nos. 1-3, 5) (Folder 16)
  - Young Socialist Forum
    - Young Socialist, 1958 (vol 2, no. 1) (Box 10., Folder 1)
    - Young Socialist Forum
      - 1959 (vol. 2, no. 2) (Folder 2)
      - 1960 (vol. 3, nos. 1, 2) (Folder 2)
  - Young Socialist League. Left Wing Caucus -- Left Wing Bulletin, 1957 (vol. 3, nos. 1, 2) (Folder 4)